Master! Master!
お師様 お師様 なにか近づいてます
Something's approaching.
It's two people.
二人です 一人は赤笛なのですか
One's a Red Whistle... and the other one...
もう一人が 探窟家ですらないような
doesn't even seem to be a cave raider...
Shall I ready the gondola?
ゴンドラの準備は
Master...?
お師様
これが シーカーキャンプ
So this is the Seeker Camp, huh?
It's really quite high up there...
随分高いところにあるんだな
Huh? Speaking of that...
あれ そういえば
What's wrong?
どうしたんだ
Um, well...
うん ええとね
I heard the Seeker Camp always has a lookout on duty.
シーカーキャンプには いつも見張りさんがいるんだって
So when someone starts approaching,
I was told they lower the gondola for them...
だから 近づくだけでゴンドラ下ろしてくれるって聞いたんだけど
A Red Whistle... A robot...
赤笛に ロボット
They might be feeling wary...
警戒されているかもしれないな
Reg, are you able to stretch your arm up there?
レグ あそこまでて伸ばせる
Maybe with both arms, or...
両手なら或いは
Let's give it a try.
やってみよう
Seems I managed to re-
なんとか届き
Reg, what's wrong?
レグ どうしたの
Something has...
何かに 腕を 掴まれた
grabbed...
my arms.
まだ生きてたんだ あのガキ
So she's still alive... that brat.
True secrets do not lie concealed
in the darkness of night or in clever traps,
真の秘密とは 夜の闇や巧妙な罠の中ではなく
but rather are hidden deep within people.
人の奥底にこそ隠れている
By spending many moons in such an isolated place,
それは隔絶された場所で時を重ねて 純度を高め
their purity is refined,
and they gradually transform into strange enigmas...
得体のしれない 謎へと変わってゆく
Riko, you alright?
リコ 大丈夫か
Oh, my... Well done enduring the ascent.
よく登ってこれたね
Although the strain is somewhat lightened around here,
この辺は負荷が緩くなっているとは言え
I suspect that was still hard on children
such as yourselves.
子供にはきつかったろうに
U-uh, I'm...
あ あの私
My name's Riko.
リコといいます
Riko!
リコ
I know! You're Lyza's kid, right?
知ってるよ ライザの子だね
How filthy...
汚いなぁ
Oh, I see the boy is doing fine.
おや 少年は平気なのかね
Now that I've seen her up close... She's towering...
近くで見てわかったが 大きい
I bet she's over two meters tall...
身長は2メートル以上あるんじゃないのか
Her hair...
あの頭 どう撫で付けたらああなるんだ
How does she smooth it down to get it to look like that?
On top of that...
それに
there's that white whistle.
あの白い笛
This woman must be the White Whistle...
この女が 白笛「動かざるオーゼン」
Ozen the Immovable!
Daremo ga sakaraezu ni mogutteiku
誰もが逆らえずに潜っていく
その目を灯火より輝かせて
Sono me o tomoshibi yori kagayakasete
Mezasu saki wa fukaku
目指す先は深く まっすぐに迷い込む
Massugu ni mayoikomu
Kuchiaketa naraku no wana
口開けた奈落の罠 真実の跡を追いかけよう
Shinjitsu no ato o oikakeyou
Ima kotae ga mitsukaru nara zenbu nakushitemo ii
今答えが 見つかるなら 全部失くしてもいい
Sono koe o hanasanai youni kodama ga mada hibiiteru
その声を 離さないように 木霊がまだ響いてる
羅針盤はずっと 闇を指したまま逃げ場のない 方へ
Rashinban wa zutto
Yami o sashita mama
Nigeba no nai
Hou e
Sore ga noroi demo
それが呪いでも 鼓動は本物
Kodou wa honmono
二度と憧れは 止まらない
Nidoto akogare wa tomaranai
Seeker Camp
この笛 また見る事になるとはねぇ
This whistle... to think that I'd actually see it again...
Um... you must be Ozen... right?!
あの あなたがオーゼンさん ですよね
I heard you're the one who found that whistle.
その笛を見つけてくれたって
That's right. I'm Ozen.
そうだよ 私がオーゼンだよ
W-well...
あ あの
Thank you for saving me!
助けてくれてありがとうございます
I heard about it from Leader!
リーダーから聞いたんです
He said when I was born in the Abyss,
I was placed in a Curse-Repelling Vessel,
アビスの中で生まれた私を「呪い除けの籠」に入れて
それで お母さんと一緒に地上まで運んでくれたって
and then, together with my mother,
you carried me to the surface!
Ah, you know...
ああ あれね
that thing was heavy,
重くてさ 何度も途中で捨てていこうと思ったよ
and along the way I thought about
just abandoning you many times.
This really takes me back...
思い出すなぁ 大事な「鐘」まで放置してさぁ
We even had to leave behind that precious Bell.
置いとけば「あの子」も来てくれたんだよなぁ
If only I had left you there,
that kid would've come with me.
Such a pity I did what I did.
惜しいことしたな
お師様
Master...
You're a Red Whistle, right?
君は赤笛だろう
You should know it's not allowed...
coming to a place like this.
だめだろうに こんな所まで来ちゃ
I...
私 お母さんに呼ばれたんです
was summoned by my mother!
So that's why Reg and I
are going to the bottom of the netherworld!
それで レグと一緒に「奈落の底」に行くんです
So, uh, as soon as I ask some things about my mother,
we'll be gone before you know it...
だからその お母さんの事だけ聞いたらすぐに出ていきますから
So, please...
だから
Oh, I see.
あーそう
So that's it.
そうなんだ
Yes...
And you deduce that makes it
okay for you to come here?
それは君らがここに来ていい理由になるのかい
I-I'm sorry.
ご ごめんなさい
That said, I'm quite interested in how a Red Whistle
even managed to make it down here.
とは言っても
赤笛がどうやってここまで来られたかには興味があるけどね
Marulk.
マルルク
Yes, Master.
はい お師様
この子達の話聞いといて
Listen to what these kids have to say.
You want ME to do that?
僕がですか
Should be easier for children to talk to a fellow child.
子供同士の方が話しやすかろ
Uh, ah...
I still have some things to attend to, you see.
私はまだやることあるからさ
I'll hear you out tomorrow.
話しは明日聞かせてあげよう
Well, both of you, here you are...
あのお二人とも これを
Ah, blue whistles!
蒼笛
Just while you're here.
ここにいる間だけ
It would be a pain to keep having to explain to other
cave raiders why a couple of Red Whistles are here.
他の探窟家に赤笛がここにいる理由を一々説明するのも面倒かろ
保険として これは預かっておくお
As a bit of insurance, I'll be holding onto this.
I'll exchange it for those blue whistles when you leave.
出る時にその蒼笛と交換だ
Please stay the night here.
今日は泊まっていきたまえ
And make sure to really give your bodies a good scrub...
きちんと体も洗っておくように
I can't stand how bad you reek of vomit.
まったくゲロ臭くてかなわん
First of all, I'll show you around a bit.
ま まずはここをご案内しますね
This Seeker Camp has been built
within the hollows of a tree called a Great Porta.
このシーカーキャンプは
大ボルタという樹のウロ穴を利用して 作られているんです
Even now, construction to expand the interior frame
is still progressing little by little.
今も少しずつ 内側を枠を広げて建て増ししているんですよ
I hear the roots of this Great Porta
extend outside the Abyss...
この大ボルタの根っこは アビスの外
stretching all the way to the seafloor.
遠く海の底まで伸びているそうです
Has anyone actually verified that?
誰か確かめたのかい
It's just speculation, apparently.
憶測だそうです
The roots take in nutrients
that have accumulated on the seafloor,
海の底に積もった栄養を撮るから
so the tree can grow this big even though
only limited light is reflected by the force field here.
力場からの光が薄くても大きく育つとか
Look.
ほら そこの壁とかウロ穴の内側なんです
This wall right there is the inside of a tree hollow.
I wonder if it won't grow too big and end up
getting all tangled up...
育ちすぎて絡め取られたりしないのだろうか
Please use this room.
ここ使ってください
The bath is over there.
お風呂そっちです
It's actually used for washing Relics, though...
ほんとは遺物を洗う場所ですけど
I'll go first! I'm gonna get nice and clean!
私行ってくる
綺麗になってくる
Oh.
Flowers of Fortitude...
「不屈の花」トコシエコウと言ったっけ
Aren't they also called Eternal Fortunes?
本当にどこにでもあるんだな
They really are everywhere...
Reg, I know you're a robot,
but there's something strange about you...
レグさんは ロボットなのに不思議ですね
Until Riko told me, I thought you were a human.
リコさんに言われるまではヒトだと思っていました
So, I was a bit surprised
when I saw your arms extend like that.
だから腕が伸びた時はちょっとびっくりしましたけど
I don't really even think of myself as a robot...
僕も自分がロボだとはあまり思えないんだ
What the heck am I in the first place...?
そもそも一体なんなのか
Is something the matter?
どうされました
"Marulk"... Is it okay if I call you that?
マルルク でいいのかな
Yes!
はい
Actually, I also have something I find strange...
実は僕も 不思議に思ってることがあってだな
What might that be?
何ですか
Ask away, and I'll answer if I can!
僕に答えられることならなんなりと
その
Um...
Are you a girl?
君は女なの
Huh?!
So cold!
さむっ
I see! So you have it tough too, then!
なるほど 君も大変なんだな
Seems we both have our share of troubles!
お互い苦労するな
やだなぁレグさん
Oh, come on now, Reg!
I haven't had anything that bad done to me!
僕 そんなことされてませんよ
Oh, I see you two are getting on well!
おや 二人共仲良しになってる
Sorry, Reg, I need something to dry off with...
ごめんレグ 何か拭くもの
ぼ 僕着替えとっておきます
I'll go get a change of clothes!
お腹減ってませんか
Are you hungry?
これ 残り物ですけど
These are leftovers, but go right ahead...
Marulk, you're about my age,
but I see you're already a Blue Whistle.
マルルクちゃんは私と同じぐらいなのに
もう蒼笛なんだね
Yeah...
蒼笛になれるのは15歳からですが
Usually you can't become
a Blue Whistle until you turn 15...
白笛の直弟子ということで「特別」らしいです
but it seems being a personal apprentice
of a White Whistle makes me a special case.
Right after I had an accident and collapsed,
Master found me and took me in.
僕 事故で行き倒れてた所をお師様に拾われて
And I've been here ever since.
それ以来ずっとここにいるんです
Oh? You have no plans to return to the surface?
地上へは帰らないの
I'm sensitive to sunlight, so I can't live up on the surface.
僕 日の光に弱くて
地上で暮らせないんです
Oh? Is that so?
そうなんだ
Well now, let's eat!
さぁ 頂きましょ
いただきます
Thanks for the food!
Ever since Master took me in, I've offered my services
as a sentry here at the Seeker Camp.
お師様 僕を拾って以来
ずっとシーカーキャンプの防人を買って出てるんです
「一々地上に戻らなくていい」って理由らしんですが
I was told that would make it so that I
"won't have to return to the surface time after time"...
Of course, it's probably also something
she wants deep down.
もちろん本心も入っているんでしょうけど
I truly have been treated well here...
本当に良くしてもらってるんです
何だか怖そうな人だったけど
She seems kind of scary, but she's a good master, huh?!
いいお師匠さんだね
ええ 本当に
Yes, truly.
Hey, Marulk...
なあ マルルク
What is it?
なんですか
What's with the Relics you've got in this room?
この部屋にある遺物はなんなんだい
Riko's started playing around with them...
リコがいじり始めてしまったが
Oh, that's okay.
大丈夫ですよ
Those won't be brought up to the surface, anyway.
あれらは地上へ持っていかないものですから
Those are the ones left over
after sorting various Relics collected in this area...
この辺で採れた遺物を選別した残り
They're grade-4 Relics, you see.
四級遺物なんですよ
これ四級遺物なんだ
So these are grade-4 Relics, then!
ほら レグ見て
Look, Reg, check this out!
This one here is my Sun Sphere.
こっちが私の「太陽玉」
Although it's similar, the one found down here
has a more complex shape.
似てるけど ここで採れた方が複雑な形してる
I hear that Relics tend to have more complex shapes
the deeper down they're found.
遺物って深層にあるもの程複雑な形をしてるのが多いそうですよ
Oh...
ほう
About forty percent of the Relics
collected around here are egg-shaped ones.
この辺で採れるものは まだ四割くらいはタマゴ型の遺物なんです
Even though they're tools used by people
in the distant past...
大昔の人が使ってた道具なのに 不思議ですね
They're mysterious, aren't they?
I'm jealous.
いいなぁ 掘りたいなぁ
I wanna excavate some.
もっと泊まっていてくれれば探窟もできるのに
If you were to stay here longer,
I'm sure you could do some cave raiding.
そうだ
That's it! I'll go ask Master if it's okay!
僕お師様にお願いしてみます
So won't you please stay a bit longer
and cave raid around here?
もう少しここで探窟とかしていきませんか
Huh?! That would be alright?!
いいの
It's the first time kids around my age have come here...
同い年ぐらいの子がここに来たのって初めてで
I'd like to spend more time with you two
so we can work together and such.
ぼく お二人と一緒にもっとお仕事とかしたいです
Me too! I'd also like to do that!
私も 私もしたい
Oh!
ごめんねマルルクちゃん
Sorry, Marulk...
Huh...?
まだ奈落の底にいるお母さんがどんな感じか分からなくて
My mother's at the bottom of the netherworld,
and I still don't know how she's doing...
So, I'm not sure whether or not
I should be hurrying down there...
だから急いでいいのかどうかも分からなくて
分からないから 急がなくちゃいけないんだ
Since I'm not sure, I have to hurry.
I see...
そうですか
Well then, let's chat as much as we can today.
じゃ 今日は沢山お話しましょう
That's what my master has instructed me to do, anyway!
ぼくお師様からそうするように言われてますし
Yeah!
I need to pee...
おしっこ
オーゼンさん
Ozen?
Is anyone in there?
誰かいるの
What the heck... was that?
何だったの あれ
There, there, Riko.
まあまあリコさん
I used to do that too until a couple of years ago.
ぼくも一昨年までやってましたし
But, Riko, why was it MY bed that you wet?
しかしリコ なぜまた僕の寝床で寝小便を
I-I did my best to find the toilet!
ちゃ ちゃんとおトイレ行こうとしたんだもん
But...
でも 夜起きて探している時に 私見たの
when I woke up in the middle of the night
and looked for it...
I saw something.
It didn't seem of this world...
まるでこの世にものじゃないみたいで
I got incredibly scared...
私 ものすごく怖くなっちゃって
そんなレグのとこ潜ってたらそのまま
So I dove into Reg's bed and that's when...
Oh, come on, Riko.
やだなぁリコさん
We've never had any reports of ghosts
here at the Seeker Camp.
シーカーキャンプにお化けの噂はありませんよぉ
B-but...
で でも
That's right, Riko.
そうだぞリコ
Reg...?
レグ
S-such fantastical things...
そ そんな非現実的な い いるんだろ
a-are out there, right?
死体によく似た生き物とか
Living creatures that look like corpses and stuff...
そんなのお母さんの封書にもなかったもん
That kind of stuff wasn't even in
Mother's sealed letter, you know!
お師様
Master!
Sounds like you're having
an interesting conversation here.
面白そうな話をしているね
U-um... This is, uh... I'm sorry!
あ あの これはその
ごめんなさい
Oh, I see.
ああ そうか
It's not a matter of you not noticing,
君は気づいてないのではなく
「あの子」にもハボルグにも何も知らされてないのか
it's more that neither that kid nor Hablog
told you anything, huh?
Um, what are you talking about...?
あの それって何の
Would you like to know?
知りたいかい
Huh?
Well, yes.
はい
In that case, follow me.
だったら
付いておいで
Otherwise, you best forget what you saw.
そうじゃなければ 見たことは忘れるんだね
レグ
Reg...
This morning, I heard from Marulk all about you two.
君達の事は 今朝マルルクから聞いたよ
Just to confirm, you're trying
to follow Lyza's trail, correct?
確認したいんだけどさ
君はライザの行方を追っているとか
はい 私は母さんに呼ばれたんです
Yes! My mother has called for me!
こいつが上がっただろうに
Didn't this thing reach the surface?
ライザは死んでいる 君が母を追う旅はここで終わりだよ
Lyza is dead.
Your journey to chase after your mother ends here.
オーゼンさんはどこでその笛や封書を見つけたんですか
Ozen, where exactly did you find
that whistle and the sealed letter?
At a grave.
墓だよ
Huh?!
もう何日前だったかな
How many days ago was it, I wonder...
The fourth layer...
四層「巨人の盃」の奥にトコシエコウの群生地があってね
In the far reaches of the Goblet of Giants,
there's this cluster of Eternal Fortunes, you see...
and a grave had been dug there.
そこに墓が出来てんだよ
あそこさ ライザが好きな場所だったんだ
You know, Lyza always liked that place.
No way...
そんな
But, Mother is calling for me-
でも お母さんが私を呼んで
That's not Lyza's handwriting.
それライザの字じゃないよ
Huh?!
I don't know how such a thing got mixed in there,
何故そんなものが紛れてたのか知らないけどさ
but Lyza wouldn't write something like that
even as a joke.
ライザはいたずらでもそんな字は書かないよ
Oh?
あれ 君が奈落の底を目指す理由はなんだっけ
What was your reason for
aiming for the bottom of the netherworld again?
I-I want to go and check for myself...
わ 私 自分で確かめに
What a fine idea.
それは名案だ
Are you going to dig up her grave?
墓でも暴いてみるかね
B-besides...
そ それに 封書にあった「謎の人影」もレグに関係が
What about the connection between Reg
and the mysterious figure mentioned in the letter...?
I see.
なるほどね
What is this place?
ここはなんだい
My chamber.
私室さ
You've followed me here
because you want to know, right?
知りたいからついてきたんだろう
Come inside.
入りなよ
Sora ni ukanderu hikaru nami o
空に浮かんでる光る波を束ねて虹の橋をかけよう
Tabanete niji no hashi o kakeyou
危うい足場 滑るスロープ
Ayaui ashiba, suberu slope
過去と未来の道標
Kako to mirai no michishirube
君の左手 僕の右手を
Kimi no hidarite, boku no migite o
繫いで繫げてはじめよう
Tsunaide tsunagete hajimeyou
いつも そばに いるよ
Itsumo soba ni iru yo
過去も 今も 未来も
Kako mo ima mo mirai mo
だから迷わずに歩いていこう
Dakara mayowazu ni aruiteikou
色とりどりの夢 重ねて
Irotoridori no yume kasanete
明日はどこに向かう
Ashita wa doko ni mukau
君と一緒にいれたら 世界は輝きだすよ
Kimi to issho ni iretara, sekai wa kagayakidasu yo
最果ての地に咲く花を探そう
Saihate no chi ni saku hana o sagasou
Next Episode
The Unmovable Sovereign